Tariq Ali

Software Engineer - Builder of Meaningful and Useful Things

tra38@nau.edu

Summary

After working as a web developer for a local non-profit and completing several technical side-projects, I have decided to transition to a career of full-time web programming. My goal is to produce meaningful apps that solve real-world problems.

My previous experience in journalism, real estate, and teaching has allowed me to easily understand and resolve complex issues. By researching and analyzing information, and then conveying that information to the rest of my team, I am able to more effectively produce useful applications for my clients.

I love talking about programming and web development. Email me at tra38@nau.edu.

Experience

Freelance Software Engineer at Ramal Tech

April 2017 - Present

- Contributing to Gitcoin.co, a freelancing web application focused on open-source projects. The project uses Python, Django, jQuery, Docker, and the Ethereum blockchain.
- Maintained an educational web app for Metis (a subsidiary of Kaplan) that teaches data science concepts, which uses Ruby on Rails on the backend and Angular 1.X on the front-end.
- Advised a client on how to bring an organic milk delivery business to market, helping them maintain their Wordpress website and building out an admin dashboard that uses Ruby on Rails.
- Built a report generator for athletes using Calyx (a Ruby gem) and created a Ruby on Rails website for gathering reviews about athletic programs using jQuery and RailsAdmin.

Software Design Engineer (Contract) at Microsoft

July 2017 - November 2017 (5 months)

- Participated in a project to automate the interview scheduling process at a department, with an emphasis on helping the team build an internal .NET (C#) web application. Wrote client-side and server-side validation for user input, wrote automated tests and manual test cases, and set up a build process. Conducted some initial research into PowerApps and Microsoft Flow to help the rest of the team incorporate these technologies into the automation project.
- Participated in a project to help identify critical issues within an application, and presented this project to other people within the organization. Wrote C# and C++ code to instrument telemetry, and used internal tools to generate e-mail alerts based on that telemetry.

Software Engineer at Firespring

February 2016 - December 2016 (11 months)

- Developing and maintaining websites for Firespring's clients, including Yoganonymous (a Yoga social networking website), SL Green, Fisher Brothers, and Nebraska Educational Telecommunications . Focused on backend web development and front-end JavaScript. Used JQuery, RailsAdmin, RSpec, CoffeeScript, and Ruby on Rails. Worked on a team of 4-6 people.
- Worked on technological "spikes" to determine the feasibility of new projects (examples: setting up a insurance rate calculator using a reverse-proxy using Node JS, rebuilding an internal website using ReactJS, testing an online form using RSpec and FactoryGirl).
- Worked with account managers to determine clients' problems and to discover possible solutions to their problems
- Reviewed other people's pull requests, conducting "code reviews" and "Quality Assurance" tests as appropriate.
- Participated in an Agile work environment with weekly developer meetings and daily standups, where we discussed ideas and suggestions to improve our team's performance.

Web Developer at Serene Technologies

September 2015 - January 2016 (5 months)

- Maintain the backend of Solaro (an educational web application built in Ruby on Rails).
- Build the "UTradeBook" web app (a website allowing people to buy and sell books and notes) using Ruby on Rails and Bootstrap.

Web Developer at Digital Fractal Technologies Inc.

September 2015 - January 2016 (5 months)

• Develop a "Content Management System" to allow users to update their own "tour guide" mobile applications, with Sinatra (a Ruby framework) and Bootstrap.

Administrative Assistant and Webmaster

January 2014 - January 2015 (1 year 1 month)

Created and maintained a Wordpress website for a 501(c) non-profit organization, and sent out periodic newsletters about the organization. Developed several other Wordpress websites for Dr. Syed Azeemuddin as well.

Created, maintained, and entered information into databases. Answered e-mail messages and give information, took messages, or transferred e-mails to appropriate individuals.

Algebra I Tutor ("Apollo Fellow") at Houston ISD

February 2014 - May 2014 (4 months)

Organized and implemented a math tournament to help encourage students to study for the Algebra I STAR test. Provided tech support during this math tournament, and selected the software used during the tournament.

Tutored 9th grade students in Algebra I to help students be able to pass their STAR exams. Administered the "Apollo 20" curriculum designed to reteach Algebra I concepts to these high school students, and kept track of students' progress.

Private Tutor

August 2012 - May 2014 (1 year 10 months)

Tutored high school students in mathematics, science, and English. Assisted students with homework assignments. Administered examinations and kept track of students' progress.

Government Instructor at Lone Star College

January 2013 - January 2014 (1 year 1 month)

Taught Government courses to community college students. Provided customer service to my students. Created, maintained, and entered information (student grades) into databases. Prepared course materials such as syllabi, homework assignments, and handouts.

Government Instructor at Alvin Community College

August 2012 - January 2014 (1 year 6 months)

Taught Government courses to community college students. Provided customer service to my students. Created, maintained, and entered information (student grades) into databases. Prepared course materials such as syllabi, homework assignments, and handouts.

Real Estate Agent at American Brokers Realty Group

August 2007 - August 2010 (3 years 1 month)

Showed clients houses that they could purchase and assisted said clients in purchasing them. Assisted clients in selling their properties. Determined the value of houses through "comparisons". Wrote 'real estate contracts' to expedite the buying and selling of homes. Provided customer service to my clients.

Journalist at Breek Publishing & Marketing/Mosaic Media Network

January 1999 - August 2010 (11 years 8 months)

Conducted research, and then periodically wrote political and religious articles utilizing this research. Explained complex topics using easy-to-understand language.

Education

Dev Bootcamp

Certification, Web Design, Ruby, Javascript, Git, 2015 - 2015

Activities and Societies: 2015 Bumblebees Cohort

Northern Arizona University

Master's degree, Political Science and Government, 2010 - 2012

Arizona State University

Bachelor's Degree, History and Political Science, 2006 - 2010

Activities and Societies: Model United Nations

Tariq Ali

Software Engineer - Builder of Meaningful and Useful Things

tra38@nau.edu



Contact Tariq on LinkedIn